Alan Guedes — C.V. ☑ a.guedes@ucl.ac.uk • ③ alanlivio .github.io ③ alanlivio ③ alanlivio

Shorbio

I am a Computer Scientist (Ph.D. & Postdoc) interested in Machine Learning (ML) methods for the next generation of immersive systems and graph-based data. My career can be seen threefold. In research, I worked on research Multimedia & ML projects, contributed to communities (Springer, ACM SIGMM, and SBC WebMedia), and have been awarded research funding. In teaching, I co-supervised students, acted as a lecturer on under- and post-graduate courses, and organized workshops to promote student interest in public engagement. In industry, I added value to it through open source and standards in TV forums (ITU-T SG16 and BR TV Forum). ¹

Experiences

Work

UCL, LASP Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML project

2021-today

Highlights: ACM SIGMM committees and workshop organizer; co-supervised undergrad students.

- SpheryStream project funded by EPSRC to Improve 360-video streaming with profile-based methods

PUC-Rio. TeleMidia Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML & Multimedia projects

2017-2020

Highlights: project PI; team leader; standards contributions; SBC WebMedia committees and workshop organizer (students for social impact); co-supervised under/postgrad students; postgraduate lecturer assistant.

- VideoMR project, funded by Microsoft & RNP to detect inappropriate content in video scenes;
- AML (Anti-Money Laundry) project, funded by BTG Bank, to detect financial transactions risk and anomaly detection;
- GT-RAP project, funded by RNP, to develop a blockchain-based system for academic certificates.

Dynavideo, TV Division

Software engineer
Highlights: multiple awarded social impact projects.

2012-2013

- Brasil4D project, funded by World Bank, to transmit interactive TV content with social features to low-income families. Its results were published in a public report

Education

PUC-Rio

Ph.D. in Informatics. Thesis on Multimodal-multiuser support in multimedia scene descriptions 2013–2017 Highlights: thesis concepts used in SBTVD standard; industry committees.

- PUC-Rio Ginga, funded by PUC-Rio Software Licenses, to develop a reference implementation for TV manufacturers;
- SBTVD Conformance Test Suite project, funded by Brazilian Ministry of Science and Technology, to be used by TV manufacturers

UFPB

MSc. in Informatics. Thesis on Multi-device support in TV app stores

2010-2012

Highlights: thesis concepts used in the awarded Brasil4D project; undergraduate lecturer; project leader

- ${\sf GingaStore},$ funded by RNP, to design a broadband system to deliver TV applications;
- Art TVDI, funded by RNP, to design agile methods for TV applications development;

HEPR

BSc. in Computer Science. Final report on Component-based architecture for TV middleware

2005-2009

- Ginga CDN, funded by RNP, to develop reusable TV middleware components.
- Tutor on Analysis and design of Algorithms;
- Part-Time software developer at Dynavideo TV Division to prototype TV software in ST boards.

¹See certificates at https://alanlivio.github.io/certificates.pdf

Research

Publications.	
Google Scholar shows 40+ published papers, 100+ citations, h-index 6. See below recent and some publications.	e selected
Elsevier Book Chapter	2022
ACM Multimedia Systems.	2022
·	2016, 2020
IEEE Symposium on Multimedia (ISM).	2020
SBC WebMedia 2020, 2020, 2020, 2021, 2	
ACM Symposium on Document Engineering.	2019
IEEE Multimedia Signal Processing.	2019
Committees.	2019
ACM, Special Interest Group on Multimedia	
·	2020-today
- Multimedia conference: reviewer (2022), area chair (2022), reproducibility chair (2023)	
 Multimedia Systems (ACM MM): MMVE review (2021, 2022, 2023) and demo chair (2022) Immersive Experiences (ACM IMX) conference: reviewer (2022) and area chair (2022) QoMex conference (ACM QoMEX): reviewer (2023) 	
BR Computing Society (SBC), Web&Mulimedia Committee	
Steering Committee 20	2021-today
Reviewer and chairing - WebMedia conference reviewer (2017-today), chair of Undergrad workshop (2018), chair of Demos (2019-2022), and chair of Social Impact Workshop (2019-2022)	2017-today Workshop
Springer	
	2022-today
 Journal of Multimedia Tools and Applications: reviewer (2022, 2023) Iberoamerican Conference on TV Applications and Usability: reviewer (2020, 2021, 2022) Brazilian TV Forum (SBTVD) 	
	2017-2021
International Telecommunication Union (ITU)	
· · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · ·	2017-2021
Teaching	
UCL	
Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.	2022-today
SBC WebMedia	
	2018-2022
PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (30+)	2019
Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (30+).	2013
Japan International Cooperation Agency	2013
Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (30+)	2012
RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (30+)	2011
UFPB Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (15-	i+) 2010
Funding & Awards	
Microsoft&RNP	
Approved as PI in VideoMR project	2019

ACM	
SIGMM Travel Award for MMSys	2022
SIGHI Gary Marsden Travel Award for IMX	2022
SIGWeb Travel Award for DocEng	2019
Multiple TV associations	
FRIDA Innovative TV technological solutions award for Brasil4D project	2014
SET Conference award on Best TV interactivity solution for Brasil4D project	2013
PremioTV on Innovation and Creativity for Brasil4D project	2013
ITU	
IPTV Application Challenge User-friendliness for GingaStore project	2012
Skills	
Teaching : Course design. Presentation skills. Programing : Python, TensorFlow, Bash, C++, Lua, Java, JavaScript, Latex, Docker. Social : Good and empathic communication. Positive, make-it-happen, teamwork, lead-by-example Languages : Portuguese (mother tongue), English (fluent), and Spanish (fluent).	
Training UCL	
Diversity and Inclusion; People Management Essentials	2023
Fundamentals in Research Funding; Data Protection; Data Protection for Researchers; GDPR	2022
Nature	
Narrative Tools for Researchers	2023
Focus on Peer Review.	2022
ΙΤυ	
ITU-T A.1: Working Methods of ITU-T Study Groups	2023
Poforoncos	

- References
- Laura Toni, I.toni@ucl.ac.uk. Postdoc supervisor at UCL.
- Simone DJ Barbosa, simone@inf.puc-rio.br. Ph.D. supervisor at PUC-Rio.
- Marcelo Moreno, moreno@ice.ufjf.br. ITU SG-16/Q13 and SBTVD collaborator.
- $-\ Roberto\ Azevedo,\ roberto. azevedo @disneyresearch.com.\ Tele Midia\ collaborator.$